welcome to the manulife income plus
videocasts
today we're going to discuss registered
retirement income funds riffs and how to
maximize the value of your rif using
income plus
if you currently own registered
retirement savings plans
rrsps you probably know they must be
cashed in or rolled over by the end of
the year in which you reach age 71.
but if you convert those rrsps to cash
your retirement nest egg will be subject
to taxation immediately
putting your retirement savings into a
rift allows you to shelter the bulk of
your funds from immediate taxation rift
plans are designed to provide people
with a stream of retirement income over
time and you only pay income tax on the
portion you withdraw in a given year
in addition by converting your rrsps to
a rift your investments have the
opportunity to continue growing tax
deferred
ideally rifts provide retirement income
for life but up until now no rick has
been able to guarantee that result
giftselect with income plus from
manulife investments provides a
guaranteed stream of income
starting as early as age 65
that lasts for your lifetime
regardless of the performance of your
investments
what does that mean to someone in or
entering retirement
let's look at an example
marie is a 66 year old retiree
she transfers 500 000 to a gift select
income plus rift contract in november
and her money is invested in a balanced
portfolio
marie could begin to take guaranteed
annual income of twenty five thousand
dollars per year right away
that's five percent of the original five
hundred thousand dollars
but instead she waits until the new year
with income plus a five percent income
bonus is added to the guaranteed amount
because income is not available until
the second calendar year
this means marie's guaranteed income
stream will be increased to at least
twenty six thousand two hundred and
fifty dollars per year starting in
january
and even if there's no market growth
that amount will continue for life
with a rif an investor is required by
legislation to withdraw a minimum amount
each year based on a percentage of the
market value of the asset held in the
rift this minimum withdrawal amount can
vary from one year to the next
by the time marie turns 72 the
guaranteed annual income provided by
income plus has increased through resets
to
and 27
seven dollars meanwhile the rift minimum
for that year is set at forty eight
thousand one hundred and ninety four
dollars this means marie is required to
withdraw more than the income plus
guaranteed annual income amount to meet
the legislated rift minimum
marie's annual rift minimum withdrawal
may be significantly more than the
annual guaranteed income amount in some
years but she will continue to receive
the lifetime income amount that's been
guaranteed through her income plus
contract
resets which occur every third year can
capture market gains but even if the
markets decline and the market value
reduces to zero as it does in this
example
the higher guaranteed annual income will
continue for life
the first product of its kind in canada
income plus rif offers
a five percent income bonus that's added
to the guaranteed withdrawal amount in
the first year where no rift income is
required to be taken
giving your retirement income an initial
boost
automatic income plus resets every three
years for life that can lock in your
market growth and increase your future
annual guaranteed income
a guaranteed minimum income of five
percent for life even if the market
value of your investments reduces to
zero
and you can withdraw the greater of the
five percent guaranteed income or the
rift minimum for life
with income plus from manulife
investments we're providing exceptional
rift flexibility and security for
retirement
your advisor can provide additional
information about income plus and the
rules that apply to rifts
you